<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A profitable dialogue for a peruerted papist. Or a little labour of a lay men tending to the profit of a peruerted Papist: namely, by laying open vnto him his ovvne errour, in beleeuing that the Church of Rome cannot erre. Composed in dialogue maner, as it were betweene a simple lay man, and certayne graue diuines, and published onely for the benefit of the lay Papist. VVritten by R.M. gent. and student in Diuinity.</title>
            <author>R. M., student in divinity.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17149</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103258</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839015</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3409</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06697)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3409)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 715:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A profitable dialogue for a peruerted papist. Or a little labour of a lay men tending to the profit of a peruerted Papist: namely, by laying open vnto him his ovvne errour, in beleeuing that the Church of Rome cannot erre. Composed in dialogue maner, as it were betweene a simple lay man, and certayne graue diuines, and published onely for the benefit of the lay Papist. VVritten by R.M. gent. and student in Diuinity.</title>
                  <author>R. M., student in divinity.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Simon Stafford, dvvelling in the Cloth-fayre, neere the signe of the red Lion,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴ F² .</note>
                  <note>Errata on verso of F2, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Print faded in places.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Infallibility --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3409:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:3409:1"/>
A Profitable Dialogue for a peruerted Papiſt. OR A little Labour of a Lay man, tending to the profit of a peruerted Papiſt: namely, by laying open vnto him his owne errour, in beleeuing that the Church of Rome cannot erre.</p>
            <p>Compoſed in Dialogue maner, as it were betweene a ſimple Lay man, and certayne graue Diuines, and publiſhed onely for the benefit of the Lay Papiſt.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>R. M.</hi> Gent. and Student in Diuinity.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Brethren, be not children in vnderſtanding,</p> 
               <bibl>1. Cor. 14. 20.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>If God be on our ſide, who can be againſt vs?</p> 
               <bibl>Rom. 8. 31.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Seeke, and ye ſhall finde,</p> 
               <bibl>Math. 7. 7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>Simon Stafford,</hi> dwelling in the Cloth-fayre, neere the ſigne of the red Lion. 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:3409:2"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Booke.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>THis ſmall Treatiſe is diuided into two parts.</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>THe firſt part contaynes certayne proofs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that it is onely the ſociety of the faithfull, (the holy Catholike Church) that can not finally erre; and that the viſible Church of Rome (or where elſe ſoeuer) may erre. And therefore not lawfull for any one Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop on earth, to be admitted vniuerſall Biſhop, or ſupreme head of the vniuerſall Church.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>THe ſecond part confirmes the former proofes, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt proofes alſo from Antiquity, that the viſible Church of Rome doth erre in a principall poynt of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian doctrine, as namely, touching the Sacrament of the bleſſed Body and Blood of our Lord and Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3409:2"/>
            <head>The Authour to the learned Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, my ſelfe being a Lay man, and altogether vnſkilfull in Artes, I am therefore to entreat of thee (being a ſcholer) that thou wilt not ſo much regard the maner and forme of this my weake worke, as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and ſubſtance it ſelfe, which is no other thing in effect, but certaine manifeſt proofes from An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, that the Church of Rome doth erre, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by ſuch ancient witneſſes, as the Papiſts themſelues allow for lawfull; and ſo forcible are thoſe witneſſes againſt thoſe Romiſh aduerſaries, that if hereafter any of them ſhall go about to reply againſt this Treatiſe enſuing, they ſhall but thereby the more lay open their owne follies and ſhame, in ſtriuing againſt the inuincible ſtreame; for great is the Trueth, and it will preuayle: yea, what can more confound the learned aduerſary, or (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth <note n="*" place="margin">Tit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 10. 11.</note>) condemne him to erre in his owne iudgement, then to find himſelfe alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnable (without abſurd cauelling and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct dealing) to reſiſt the weakeneſſe of a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb facs="tcp:3409:3"/>
Lay man, fighting in Trueths behalfe? for notwithſtanding my Sixe demaunds to the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Papiſts, be the ſimpleſt booke that euer hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath bene brought foorth againſt them, yet are they not able to reply directly againſt it, without abſurdity. Whereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I doubt, they will ſeeme to ſkorne to vouchſafe it an anſwere.</p>
            <p>But here by the way, I acknowledge (and that ſincerely) that it is vnmeete for any Lay man, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though neuer ſo great a ſcholer, to take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the office of miniſtery in the Church, or to clime vp to the Pulpit, before he be lawfully cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to that holy and reuerend function<hi>:</hi> But for Lay men decently to inſtruct and admoniſh one another, it is no nouelty, but a thing allowable in the Church many yeeres ſince, as witneſſeth S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> who ſayth playnely, <note n="*" place="margin">Vpon the Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtle to the Colo. Chap. 3.</note> that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth teach, that Lay men ought to haue the Scriptures abundantly, and to inſtruct and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh one another, &amp;c. But if it be tolerable for Lay men to admoniſh one another, it followes then (becauſe all are not ſcholers) that ſome of them may be alſo tolerated to write ſimply and playnely, and according to that maner of ſpeach which the common vulgar ſort do vſually ſpeake, who neuer ſpeake more eloquently, then when they ſpeake trueth ſincerely and playnely, and then they thinke they ſpeake very well, if they be
<pb facs="tcp:3409:3"/>
vnderſtood very well.</p>
            <p>But perhaps, ſome learned Aduerſary will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect (according to his vſuall maner) againſt theſe proofes, which I haue here cited from ſome of the ancient Fathers, liuing in the Church aboue a thouſand yeeres ſince, that they haue bene brought forth already by diuers learned men, &amp; long ſince anſwered by learned men alſo, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in vaine for me being a Lay man vnlearned, to cite them againe, thinking that I haue but ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them here and there out of other mens workes, where they haue bene collected before, and for that cauſe likewiſe, from me the leſſe to be regarded.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being obiected, I anſwere, True it is, that the ſame proofes haue long ſince bene brought forth againſt the Aduerſaries, &amp; by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo anſwered; but how well, or how ill they haue bin anſwered, let that be tryed by thoſe Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans which are of ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d iudgement; for this I da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e auouch, that a lawfull witneſſe being brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is no leſſe then an abſurd anſwer in that man whoſoeuer, to reply, that the ſame witneſſe, in ſpeaking of one thing, doth thereby meane another<hi>:</hi> But into the ſame ſtrayte are all Heretiks brought, by reſiſting the appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t truth. And this is a principall marke to be aymed at in this our corrupt age, in which there is ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:3409:4"/>
diſſenſion and controuerſie among profeſſed Chriſtians. For if our aduerſaries might be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to anſwere ſo abſurdly, and to paſſe from one poynt to another, before ſome one poynt onely be throughly decided; all the labour wee take, to cleanſe them from their infectious ſpots of errour, would proue but labour in vayne: but (God be thanked) the faithfull know well, how to preuent the ſilly ſhiftes of Heretikes, and ſo with little labour, eyther to conuert them, or confound them: for commonly the Heretike may be condemned by his owne mouth, his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine contradicting ſome trueth in Scripture, which himſelfe profeſſeth to beleeue: for where traditions and cuſtomes of men are regarded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore holy Scripture, there ignorance doth ſoone beget errour; eſpecially if diuers things called by one name, be not ſo perfectly diſtinguiſhed, but that the one may be taken for the other.</p>
            <p>But let the ignorant learne, firſt touching faith. A true faith which worketh by loue, is one thing; and a verball or vaine faith another.</p>
            <p>Secondly, touching iuſtification; A iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before God, is one thing; and a iuſtification before men, another<hi>:</hi> for God iuſtifieth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the inward heart, (by the good tree, true faith:) but man iuſtifieth according to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward declaration, (by the fruits proceeding fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:3409:4"/>
that tree<note n="*" place="margin">Luke. 6. 43.</note>, good workes.) S. <hi>Paul</hi> treating of the firſt iuſtification, denyes not the ſecond; for he ſayth, <hi>If Abraham were iuſtified by workes, he hath wherein to reioyce, but not with God, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note n="γ" place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> S. <hi>Iames</hi> treating of the ſecond, denyes not the firſt<hi>:</hi> for he graunts, <hi>Abraham beleeuing God, it was imputed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for righteouſneſſe, &amp;c</hi> 
               <note n="γ" place="margin">Iames. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, touching the Church<hi>:</hi> The ſociety of the faithfull, which liue by true faith, (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hell gates not poſſible to preuayle againſt them) is one thing; and a viſible congregation, which may profeſſe Chriſt by words, and deny him by deeds, another.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, touching Baptiſme; the outward Sacrament, the waſhing of the outward man, is one thing, and the inward grace, the clenſing of the inward man, another.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, touching the Euchariſt: The outward Sacrament alſo, foode for the Body, is one thing; and the inward matter, euerlaſting life for the ſoule, another<hi>:</hi> and ſo foorth in the like.</p>
            <p>Now, the faithfull, knowing well the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in theſe things, and that the one may be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes taken without the other, will neuer permit the aduerſary to paſſe away vncorrected) with any vntrueth therein, be it neuer ſo little; becauſe from one error, another may enſue; but not poſſible directly, an errour to proceede from
<pb facs="tcp:3409:5"/>
trueth: for Gods word is not both Yea and Nay in one thing, but abſolutely Yea, or Nay, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth <note n="γ" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.</note>.</p>
            <p>As touching the maner of my collecting here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I may iuſtly auouch it, from the firſt authors themſelues<hi>:</hi> but admit it were otherwiſe, yet let no man be ſo vayne, as to thinke the trueth to be of leſſe force in one place then in another, but let him rather learne this wiſdome from S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that although <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Apollos,</hi> or whoſoeuer plant and water, yet it is God onely that giues the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of increaſe<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 6, 7.</note>. </p>
            <p>And becauſe God may giue that heauenly bleſſing to whom he will, and without reſpect of perſons <note n="γ" place="margin">Ephe. 6. 9.</note>, in hope of the ſame bleſſing vpon this my little labour, (rude and harſh in maner and forme, though in ſubſtance according to trueth) I will now require no more of thee (courteous Reader,) but that thou wilt permit it thy fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable paſport, (and not to reiect the maner of it, more then to reſpect the matter in it;) in ſo doing thou ſhalt declare thy ſelfe a moſt faithfull friend to the ſimple Trueth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by not iuſtly to offend any whoſoeuer.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:3409:5"/>
            <head>A profitable Dialogue for a peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Wherein he may clearely diſcerne his owne <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, in beleeuing that the Church of Rome</hi> cannot erre.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>The firſt part, briefly treating of the Church.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay man.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Iuine</hi> Auguſtine, <hi>foraſmuch as thy proper workes are of great fame &amp; eſtimation in the Church of Rome; (which now in part is fallen from that her firſt faith and integrity which ſometime thou didſt know her ſincerely to hold; (for ſhe doth now preſumptuouſly auouch, that ſhe can not erre in any ſubſtantiall poynt of the Chriſtian faith, and by reaſon of that vaine and preſumptuous opinion, ſhe is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len by euill cuſtome, into diuers errours, by which, great controuerſies among Chriſtians do ariſe;) therefore in the behalfe of many ſimple Lay people, we moſt earneſtly craue of thée (Reuerend Father) to tell vs directly thy true opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, touching the vayne opinion of them, which hold that the ſame Church cannot erre.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We certaynely perſwade our ſelues, that thy direct an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:6"/>
                     <hi>herein, will greatly preuayle with thoſe our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; for ſome of them haue written</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">N. D. Author of the Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word in his 1. booke of of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſions of England, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.</note> 
                     <hi>as a matter of great moment againſt Heretiks, that</hi> Whereſoeuer any doctrine is found in any of the Ancient Fathers, which is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted, nor noted by any of the reſt, as ſingular; that doctrine is to be preſumed to be no particular opinion of his, but rather the generall of all the Church in his dayes; for that otherwiſe it would moſt certaynly haue bin noted and impugned by others, &amp;c. <hi>Therefore whatſoeuer is ſpoken by thée (learned</hi> Aug.) <hi>not yet contradicted, they muſt thereby graunt it to be the Trueth of the Church in thy flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We confeſſe, that the true holy Catholike Church cannot finally erre; for hell gates are not able to preuayle againſt it:</hi> 
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 16. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>but this holy Catholike Church, we vnderſtand to conſiſt onely of the Elect, as our Créede witneſſeth, euen the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saynts, which without ſpot or wrinkle, Chriſt, by his precious bloud, hath made glorious to himſelfe</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Ephe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 27.</note>; <hi>for againſt all other, hell gates doe preuayle; and that doeth the Euangeliſt S.</hi> Iohn <hi>witneſſe, ſaying,</hi> 
                     <note n="d" place="margin">1. Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 19.</note> They went out from vs, but they were not of vs: for if they had bene of vs, they would haue continued with vs: But this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to paſſe, that it might appeare, that they are not all of vs, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But it is euident, that againſt whoſoeuer hell gates may preuayle, they alſo may erre: (for it is moſt true, that none can erre more, then thoſe that take the ready way to hell, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing they goe to heauen.) By which, we may well hold, (againſt the Church of Rome) that not all which receyue the outward Sacrament of Baptiſme, are then made members of that Church which cannot finally erre. And by this wée may well proue alſo, that the Biſhop of Rome may as much erre, as the meaneſt of vs Laymen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saint</hi> Ambroſe ſayth, <note n="c" place="margin">Vpon S. Luk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, the 6. Booke, &amp; 9. Chap.</note> 
                     <hi>that</hi> The foundation of the
<pb facs="tcp:3409:6"/>
Church is ſayth. If thou wilt be a Rock <hi>(ſayth he)</hi> thou ſhalt be in the Church, becauſe the Church is vpon a Rock; if thou be in the Church, the gates of hell ſhall not preuayle againſt thee: the gates of hell, are the gates of death, but the gates of hell, cannot be the gates of the Church; And what are the gates of death (that is to ſay, the gates of hell) but euery one of our ſeuerall ſinnes? &amp;c. <hi>And more in an other place,</hi> 
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Vpon the 40. Pſalm.</note> Where Peter the Rock is, <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> there is <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     </hi> Church, where the Church is, there is no death, but eternal life; and therefore he added, And the gates of hell ſhall not preuayle againſt it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He then that liues and dyes in his ſinnes, both liues and dyes out of the vnity of that holy Church, againſt which, hell gates can not preuayle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But for theſe things, ſpeake, diuine</hi> Auguſtine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſonne,</hi> 
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Againſt Creſconius the 2, booke Chap. 21, 22.</note> The Apoſtle Paul doth ſay, <note n="h" place="margin">Ephe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 2.</note> that the Church is made ſubiect to Chriſt; The Church therefore ought not to preferre her ſelf before Chriſt, that ſhe ſhould thinke to be able to baptize thoſe which are iudged or condemned by him; but not poſſible of her ſelfe to baptize them, becauſe he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes iudgeth truely, but the Iudges of the Church, as being men, are often deceyued; Therefore foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as pertayneth to the viſible miniſtery, both good and euill baptize: But by them he doth inuiſibly bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize, of whom both the viſible baptiſme, and the inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible grace is. Both good and euill then may ſprinkle: but to waſh the conſcience, not any can do it, but he which is alwayes good <note n="*" place="margin">None but God alwaies good.</note>. And by this alſo, by reaſon of the euill and polluted conſcience, the Church is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of ſuch as are condemned by Chriſt. They
<pb facs="tcp:3409:7"/>
are not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Body of Chriſt, which is the Church, becauſe Chriſt can not haue conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned members, &amp;c. <hi>(Who then can poynt to thoſe that can not erre?)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Although both good and euill <note n="i" place="margin">In his booke of the vnity of the Church, chap. 18.</note> may giue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the Sacrament of Baptiſme, yet not any are ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually regenerated &amp; built together in the body and members of Chriſt, but the good.</p>
                  <p>Doubtleſſe, in the good is that Church, by whom it is ſayd, <note n="k" place="margin">Canti. Cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 2.</note> Like a Lilly among the thornes, ſo is my Loue among the daughters, &amp;c. For it is in thoſe that build vpon the Rocke, that is, thoſe which heare the words of Chriſt, and doe them: (for it was ſayd to Peter, <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 16. 18.</note> conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſing Chriſt the Sonne of God, And vpon this Rocke I will build my Church.) It is not then in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe which build vpon ſand, that is, thoſe which heare the words of Chriſt, and do them not; for he ſayth, <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 7. 24.</note> He that heareth my words and doeth the ſame, I will liken him to a wiſe man, which builds his houſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vpon a rocke. And in the ſame place, a little a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, he ſayth, He which heareth my words, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them not, I will liken him to a fooliſh man, which builds his houſe vpon ſand, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe then that are incorporated by the ioyning of charity, dwelling vpon the Rocke, and ſtanding toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bright as a Lilly among thornes, they ſhall verily poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſe the kingdome of God. But thoſe which buyld vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and, or are accounted as thornes, who can doubt that they ſhall not poſſeſſe the Kingdome of GOD? Truely, the Sacrament of Bapti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me profits not ſuch, &amp;c. They ſhal not poſſeſſe the kingdome of God: and therefore they are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> on the Rocke: and becauſe they are not on the Rock, without all doubt, they are not to bee accounted in the Church, becauſe vpon
<pb facs="tcp:3409:7"/>
this Rocke, ſayth he, I will build my Church, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To thoſe that are not wilfully obſtinate in erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious opinions, thou haſt ſayd inough for this matter (moſt reuerend Father:) for here thou doſt moſt plainly declare vnto vs, who they are, of whome the true Church (the Spouſe of Chriſt) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth; euen thoſe that heare the words of Chriſt, and do them: they onely build vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Rock, againſt which, hel gates cannot preuavl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>; for (as thou doſt moſt truely affirme) whoſoeuer builds not vpon that Rock, without al doubt they are not to be accounted in the true Church, becauſe vpon the ſame Rocke, that Church is built.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But what is thy opinion, touching</hi> Peter, <hi>and</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>ſucceſſours in</hi> Peters <hi>chayre, which in the new Law (as ſome ſay) is anſwerable to the chayre of</hi> Moſes? <hi>If they heare the words of Chriſt, and do them not, ſhall they yet notwithſtanding be obeyed, as men that cannot erre?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſonne,</hi> 
                     <note n="n" place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Sermon vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on S. Mat.</note> This name that he ſhould be called <hi>Peter,</hi> was giuen him of our Lord, becauſe by that figure, he might ſignifie the Church: for Chriſt is the Rocke, <hi>Peter</hi> the Chriſtian people; for that Rocke is a principall name<hi>:</hi> Therefore he is <hi>Peter</hi> from the Rocke, not the Rocke from <hi>Peter,</hi> euen as Chriſt is not called from a Chriſtian, but a Chriſtian from Chriſt. Thou art therefore <hi>Peter,</hi> (ſayth he) and vpon this Rocke which thou haſt confeſſed, vpon this Rocke which thou haſt acknowledged, (ſaying, Thou art Chriſt the Sonne of the liuing God) I will build my Church, that is, vpon my ſelfe the Sonne of the liuing God, I will buyld my Church: vpon mee, I will
<pb facs="tcp:3409:8"/>
buyld thee, not mee, vpon thee: for men (willing to be built vpon men) ſay, I verily am of <hi>Paul,</hi> but I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to <hi>Apollos,</hi> but I am of <hi>Cephas,</hi> which is <hi>Peter;</hi> But others (which would not build vpon <hi>Peter,</hi> but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Rocke) ſay, But I am of Chriſt, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12.</p>
                  <p>Many in the Church follow after earthly buſineſſes, <note n="o" place="margin">In his 46. Treatis vpon S. Iohn.</note> yet they preach Chriſt, and by them the voice of Chriſt is heard; but the ſheep follow not the hirelings, but the voyce of the Shepherd by meanes of the hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</p>
                  <p>Note, the Lord himſelfe doth declare vnto you, what hirelings are: <note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 23. 2, 3.</note> The Scribes and the Phariſes (ſayth he) ſit in the chayre of <hi>Moſes,</hi> what they ſay, do, but what they do, that do not. What other thing ſayd he, but, By hirelings, heare the voice of the Shepherd? for fitting in <hi>Moſes</hi> chayre, they teach the Law of God: therefore God teacheth by them: But if they teach their owne, neyther heare nor do, <hi>(what they ſay:)</hi> for truely, ſuch ſeeke their owne, not thoſe things which are of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It ſéemes then, by thy iudgement, that we muſt not build vpon men, of what calling or place ſoeuer, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe what they teach, be agréeable to the Law of God; and herein indéed thou dooſt follow the good counſell and aduice of bleſſed</hi> Paul, <hi>who ſayth plainely, touching the viſible Church,</hi> 
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Gala. 1. 8.</note> Though that we, or an Angell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen preach vnto you otherwiſe, then that which we haue preached vnto you, let him be accurſed, &amp;c. <hi>And thereby proues inuincibly, that no doctrine is to be receyued in the Church, (although conſtituted by the Church) contrary and beſides that pure doctrine, taught from the beginning. And the ſame thing doth S.</hi> Iohn
<pb facs="tcp:3409:8"/>
                     <hi>proue alſo,</hi> 
                     <note n="r" place="margin">1. Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 24. &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>and therefore our aduerſaries of Rome would gladly proue ſome of their owne doctrines, to be the traditions of the Church, receyued firſt from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelues: and vainely they boaſt, as a great matter againſt vs, that we are not able directly to ſhew the time when the Church of Rome fell into any Error, nor by whom ſhée was firſt brought into errour. But all this is but vaine cauelling; for the deuill hath not ſo little craft in him, as to change good to euill, ſuddenly; for then the euil could hardly take place; but by little and little, (which craft by a great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, is little or nothing perceyued at the firſt,) he brings much euill into the Church. By continuance of time, the often droppes of water haue made a hole in the hardeſt ſtone: but none could tell the time directly when that hole was made. It is ſufficient, to proue the Church of Rome to teach now, contrary to the doctrine taught in the ſame Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue a thouſand yeres ſince: which thing is eaſie to be proued by the helpe of thée and other ancient witneſſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſéeme alſo to make good and lawfull their owne Doctrines and Traditions beſides the Scriptures, by that place in the Goſpell, where our Sauiour ſayth to his Diſciples,</hi> 
                     <note n="s" place="margin">Iohn. 16. 12, 13.</note> I haue yet many things to ſay to you, but ye can not beare them now, howbeit, when he is come, which is the Spirit of Truth, he ſhall lead you into all trueth, &amp;c. <hi>But what ſayeſt thou (ancient</hi> Auguſtine) <hi>to this deluſion of theirs?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſonne,</hi> 
                     <note n="t" place="margin">In his 97. Treatis vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on S. Iohn, and in his 96, Treatis.</note> By this occaſion of the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall ſentence, (where our Lord ſayth, I haue yet many things to ſay to you, &amp;c.) all the moſt fooliſh he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes (that would be called Chriſtians) go about to colour the boldneſſe of their owne inuentions, &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:3409:9"/>
But who dares to auouch, that ſuch and ſuch are thoſe things <hi>(which Chriſt had to ſay to his Diſciples?)</hi> and, if they do auouch it, how do they proue it, &amp;c?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To this thou haſt anſwered very playne: for by this thy playne ſpeach, we well perceyue thy meaning in an other place,</hi> 
                     <note n="u" place="margin">Againſt the Epiſtle of Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Chap. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>where thou ſayeſt, that</hi> Thou ſhouldeſt not haue beleeued the Goſpell, vnleſſe the Authority of the Church had moued thee thereunto, &amp;c. <hi>Wée alſo in theſe our dayes may iuſtly auouch the ſame thing, becauſe firſt, the authority of the Church is the meanes (for the moſt part) to moue the outward man both to know and beléeue, and alſo to reuerence the holy Scriptures. But tell vs yet (reuerend Father) is that authority ſtill abſolutely to be obeyed, albeit it teach vncertayne things, which the Scripture doth not allow? or may we then lawfully forſake it, although by the ſame meanes we firſt beléeued?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſonne,</hi> 
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Againſt the ſame E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, Chap 14.</note> What haue we to do, but to forſake them that inuite vs to know things certayne, and afterwards commaund vs to beleeue things vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne? and to follow them which inuite vs firſt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that which we are not yet able to behold? that being made ſtronger by faith it ſelfe, we may attayne to vnderſtand that which we beleeue, now not men, but GOD himſelfe confirming and lightening our mindes inwardly, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>None can be ignorant <note n="y" place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Booke of Baptiſme, againſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onatiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s. Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> that the holy Canonicall Scripture, (as well of the old as of the new Teſtament) is contayned within her certayne limits, and that it is ſo preferred before all later writings of Biſhops, that whatſoeuer is certaine to be written in it, can not in
<pb facs="tcp:3409:9"/>
any wiſe be doubted or diſputed whether it be true or right. ☞ But the writings of Biſhops (which haue <note place="margin">By this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the certayney of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the vncertaynty of all other writings, he proues (by good conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) that the viſible Church may erre.</note> bene written, or which are now written after the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non is confirmed) may be lawfully reprehended, both by a more wiſe ſpeach of ſome man, which perhaps is more ſkilfull in that matter, and alſo by a more graue authority, and more learned prudence of other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; and by Councels, if perhaps any thing in them haue ſtrayed from the trueth. And euen Councels themſelues, which are gathered in any Region or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, muſt (without all doubt) giue place to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of generall Councels, which are gathered out of the vniuerſall Chriſtian world: And oftentimes the former generall Councels themſelues may be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the later, when (in any try all of matters) that is opened, which was ſhut, and that knowne, which was hidden, <note n="z" place="margin">Nothing is hid from the holy Ghoſt: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt is not aſſiſtant to thoſe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels which may be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected.</note> without any ſwelling of ſacrilegious pride, without any ſtiffe-necke of puffing arrogancy, without any contention of cankred enuy; with holy humility, with Catholike peace, with Chriſtian chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp;c. <hi>(But for this matter, I haue written at large, in my booke of the vnity of the Church.)</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vndoubtedly, theſe things from thée are moſt effectuall to proue the Church of Rome to erre, in affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that ſhe cannot erre; But yet, for more confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, we pray thée to deliuer vnto vs thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alſo, touching a principall matter of the Chriſtian faith, now in controuerſy betwéene vs, to wit, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the preſence of Chriſt in the bleſſed Sacrament of his Body and Blood. But before we procéede in that matter, we will craue a few words from</hi> Gregory <hi>the great, (ſometime Biſhop of Rome) touching the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:10"/>
                     <hi>ſupremacy of the Pope of Rome; for we take his v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall authority to be the onely cauſe, that Romes er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours haue bene ſo much ſcattered and diſperſed abroad into euery Chriſtian nation. And becauſe they hold now in Rome, that the Biſhop of Rome cannot erre, we thinke, the beſt proofe againſt them therein, is, to bring the Biſhop of Rome, againſt the Biſhop of Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Speake, diuine</hi> Gregory: <hi>what ſayeſt thou to him that is called by the name of Vniuerſall Biſhop?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gregory.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne,)</hi> If any one in the Church ſnatch to himſelfe that name, <note n="a" place="margin">In his Regiſter the 4. Booke, Epiſtle. 32.</note> then (by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all good men) when he falls which is called Vniuerſall, the vniuerſall Church falleth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her ſtate; which God forbid. But farre be that name of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy from Chriſtian hearts, by which the honour of al Prieſts is taken away, while it is fooliſhly arrogated by one to himſelfe, &amp;c. <note n="b" place="margin">In his 6. Booke, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Epiſtle.</note> I ſpeake it boldly, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer cals himſelfe vniuerſall Prieſt, or deſires to be ſo called, by the ſame pride of his, he forerunneth Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: for by pride hee preferreth himſelfe before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and by the ſame pride he is led into errour, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verily, hadſt not thou thy ſelfe bene Biſhop of Rome, the Church of Rome could hardly brooke theſe words of thine: for here thou doeſt not onely call this name, A name of Blaſphemy, but (contrary to their opinion, touching the immutable doctrine of the viſible Church) thou doeſt alſo affirme, that (by the iudgement of all good men) when he which is called V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall, falls into errour, then the vniuerſall Church falls from her ſtate alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But yet thou ſéemeſt here to ſpeake ſomewhat doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:10"/>
                     <hi>in diſcommending him onely, that doeth arrogate to himſelfe this vniuerſall authority: It may be, that thou dooſt allow the Biſhop of Rome to conſent vnto it, and ſo to take it, being offered by others.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gregory.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">In his 4. Booke, and 36. Epiſtle.</note> This name of Vniuerſal, was by the Calcedon Councell offered to one Biſhop of the Apoſtolike ſeat, in which I ſerue, (God diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) but none of my predeceſſours conſented at any time to vſe this ſo prophane a name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why would they not conſent to it?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Greg.</speaker>
                  <p>Truely, becauſe if one be called <note n="d" place="margin">In his 39. Epiſtle,</note> the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal Patriark, the name of Patriarks is taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt: But away with that, &amp;c. To conſent to that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked name, is nothing elſe, but to deſtroy faith, &amp;c. <note n="e" place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Booke, and 69. Epiſtle.</note> One to be Vniuerſal Biſhop, is to the iniury &amp; renting of the whole Church, and as we haue ſayd, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all Biſhops; for if one be vniuerſal, as he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, it remayneth that the reſt are not Biſhops, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But if the Church of Rome permit this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be lawfull, which thou dooſt ſo much gaineſay, doth any euill then come thereby? Our Lord prayed for the faith of S.</hi> Peter, <hi>(and ſo conſequently for the faith of all his ſuceſſours, according to the opinion of the aduerſary <note n="*" place="margin">In their Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh notes vpon the 28 of S. Luke, verſe, 31.</note>) that it ſhould neuer fayle. But if any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome may proue a falſe Chriſtian, and liue ſo lewdly, that he may dye a Reprobate, then vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, euery Biſhop of Rome is not the true ſucceſſour of S.</hi> Peter, <hi>vnleſſe a true faith may contradict in maners the things which it profeſſeth in words: for it was a true</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:11"/>
                     <hi>faith in S.</hi> Peter, <hi>which our Lord prayed for, to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in his Church, and not a vaine fayth. And if it be true, that the Biſhop of Rome may erre, as he is man, but not poſſible, as he is Pope, that is to ſay, although in perſon he may erre in his priuate doctrine and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, yet not poſſible to erre iudicially or definitiuely, then could it not be preiudiciall to the Church, although Antichriſt himſelfe were Biſhop of Rome, <note n="*" place="margin">See S. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> to the Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſa. and S. Barna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>d in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s 123. Epiſtle.</note> and Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Biſhop. But according to diuine reaſon, this ſéemes not agréeable to trueth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gregory.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſonne,</hi> If this be permitted to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſpoken, <note n="f" place="margin">In his 4. Booke, and 36. Epiſtle.</note> the honor of all Patriarchies is deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and perhaps when he pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſheth in errour, which is called vniuerſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll, then no Biſhop is found to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned in the ſtate of trueth, &amp;c. <hi>I ſay therefore,</hi> the vniuerſall Church <note n="g" place="margin">In his 6. Booke, and Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tle 24.</note> falleth to ruine, if one Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall fall; But farre be this vanity and fooliſhneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from my eares, &amp;c. *A true faith doth not contradict in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     </hi> things which it profeſſeth in words *: for which <note place="margin">Hom. 29 in Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng. Tit. 1.</note> cauſe it was ſayd of certayn falſe Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, by S. <hi>Paul</hi> *, that they confeſſed God in words, but denied him in deeds: &amp; by S. <hi>Iohn</hi> *, that whoſoeuer (ſayth he) know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Iohn. 2.</note> God, and keepeth not his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, is a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar. Which being ſo, we muſt examine the trueth of our faith, by conſideration of our life: for then, &amp; not otherwiſe, are we true Chriſtians, if we fulfill in works, that whereof we haue made promiſe in words, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Would to God, thy ſucceſſours had bene of the ſame mind herein, as thou and thy predeceſſours were; for then the Church vniuerſally could neuer haue bene ſo much diuided as it hath bene; for moſt true it is (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:11"/>
                     <hi>to thy ſpeach) that within leſſe time then this</hi> 200. <hi>yéeres paſt, hardly was there a Biſhop to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d remayning in that ſincere and pure doctrine, taught in the Primitiue Church, but being reuolted and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from that ſound doctrine, they all from the higheſt to the loweſt, taught lyes in hypocriſie, (euen as Saint</hi> Paul <hi>propheſted of them) forbidding to marry,</hi> 
                     <note n="h" place="margin">1. Tim. 4, 1, 2, 3.</note> 
                     <hi>and commaunding to abſtayne from meates lawfully to be eaten, with other ſuch like errours, and deceyueable doctrines. But the principall cauſe of ſuch vniuerſall euils, thou haſt playnely declared to procéede from the pride of him called vniuerſall Biſhop: which man wée take to be no better then Antichriſt himſelfe: for (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to S.</hi> Paul) <note n="i" place="margin">2. Theſſe. 2. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>he ſits hypocritically in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, in word, The ſeruant of ſeruants, but in déede, extolling himſelfe aboue all power on earth: for by vſurped authority he ſéekes not onely to be ſupreme head ouer all Biſhops, but ouer all Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtian Kings al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; which loftyneſſe was ney<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>her in thée, nor in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours, and that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> dooſt make moſt manifeſt, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by theſe playne ſpeaches here vttered, but elſewhere alſo,</hi> 
                     <note n="k" place="margin">In hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 38. Epiſtle, Chap. 82.</note> 
                     <hi>with which we reſtfully ſatiſfied herein.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſo we will conclude this firſt part, with a few words taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our late Miniſter (but now an Apoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta)</hi> Theophilus Higgons <note n="*" place="margin">Written ſince hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, in his firſt Motiue, Page 64.</note>; <hi>becauſe they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine a truth (touching this poynt) contrary to himſelf; as thus:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was a tyranny in</hi> Mezentius <hi>(ſayth he) to bynd li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing men vnto dead carkeyſes. But the wiſdome of God doth aſſure me, (and me alſo) that he will not tye the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing body of his Church, vnto the dead and putrified mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <trailer>The end of the firſt part.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:3409:12"/>
               <head>The ſecond part, treating of the <hi>Sacrament of the Bleſſed Body</hi> and Blood of our LORD and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow, diuine</hi> Auguſtine, <hi>let vs go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in that principall poynt, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the holy Sacrament: let vs cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynely know thy mind, whether Chriſt be there, after a ſpirituall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, onely for the faithfull to eate, and drinke, or after a corporal and carnall maner, as foode both for the worthy and vnworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We find in holy Scripture, that our Sauiour called</hi> 
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Iohn. 6. 35. and 10. 7. and 15. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>himſelfe Bread, called himſelfe a Doore, called him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Vine: Theſe things in a ſpiritual ſence, we know to be truely and properly ſpoken: yet according to the letter, we take them figuratiuely to be ſpoken. But wée would gladly vnderſtand from thée, what our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour meant, when he called Bread his body,</hi> 
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 26. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>and alſo what he meant, when he ſayd,</hi> Exceptye eate <note n="n" place="margin">Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3409:12"/>
the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his blood, ye haue no life in you, &amp;c. <hi>Whether theſe ſpeaches (according to the letter) were figuratiue or proper?</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> Our Lord doubted not to ſay, This is my body, <note n="o" place="margin">Againſt Adamantus, Chap. 12</note> when he gaue the ſigne of his Body, &amp;c. <note n="p" place="margin">Vpon the 3. Pſal.</note> Chriſt admitted <hi>Iudas</hi> to that Banket, in which he did deliuer to his diſciples, the figure of his Body, &amp;c. <hi>(Note this alſo)</hi> If it be a ſpeach of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, eyther forbidding a miſchieuous deed, or a hainous fact, <note n="q" place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Booke of Chriſtian doctrine, Chap. 16.</note> or commaunding a profitable thing, or a good deed, it is not figuratiue: But if it ſeeme to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund a wicked deed, and a naughty fact, or to forbid a profitable thing or a good deed, it is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue. Vnleſſe ye ſhall eate (ſayth he) the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his blood, ye ſhall not haue life in you, &amp;c. He doth ſeeme to commaund a hainous or wicked deed. It is a figure therefore, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding vs to communicate with the paſſion of our Lord, and ſweetely and profitably to lay vp in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that his fleſh was crucifyed and wounded for vs, &amp;c. <note n="r" place="margin">Vpon the 98. Pſalm.</note> The words which I haue ſpoken vnto you, (ſayth Chriſt) is ſpirit and life. <note n="s" place="margin">Iohn. 6. 63.</note> Vnderſtand ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, that which I haue ſpoken vnto you: Ye ſhall not eate this Body which ye ſee, neyther ſhall ye drinke that blood which they ſhall ſheade that crucify me: I haue commended vnto you a certayne Sacrament, which being ſpiritually vnderſtood, ſhall giue you life, &amp;c. <note n="t" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n his 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>reati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vpon S. Iohn.</note> He himſelfe doth expound, how that may be done, which he ſpake of, &amp; what it is to eate his Body, and drinke his blood. He which eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood, (ſayth he) dwelleth in me, <note n="u" place="margin">Iohn. 6. 56.</note> &amp; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n him: This it is then to eate that meate, and drinke
<pb facs="tcp:3409:13"/>
that blood, to dwell in Chriſt, and to haue Chriſt dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in him. And by this, he that dwelleth not in Chriſt, and in whom Chriſt doth not dwell, without doubt, hee neither eates his fleſh, nor drinkes his blood, ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, although carnally and viſibly, hee preſſe with his teeth, the Sacrament of his body and blood; but rather hee doth eate and drinke the Sacrament of ſo great a thing to his owne Iudgement, becauſe hee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes to come vncleane to the Sacraments of Chriſt, which no man receyues worthily, but hee which is cleane, of whom it is ſayd, <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 8.</note> Bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then it ſéemes by thée, (contrary to the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Church of Rome) that the preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament, is in ſuch a ſpirituall maner, that although the wicked may eate and drinke the ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament vnworthily, (according to S.</hi> Paul) <note n="y" place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>yet they cannot by any meanes eate and drinke Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the matter and ſubſtance thereof. Whereby thou dooſt declare this thing to be an vnſpeakeable myſtery, onely for the faithfull to vnderſtand; for it ſéemes here alſo by thée, that none can receiue the Body of Chriſt, but onely the liuely members of Chriſt, that dwell in him; ſo that as they dwell in Chriſt, Chriſt dwelleth in them: but this is not according to Tranſſubſtantiation. Therefore, to ſatiſfie our weake brethren, ſpeake yet more playne, if thou canſt (reuerend Father) and tell vs by ſome familiar example, whether any can haue true life, not eating and drinking that holy ſubſtance, and alſo whether there bée any cauſe or ſpiritual ſickneſſe in man, (eating and drinking the Body and Blood of Chriſt) to exclude him from that eternall life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3409:13"/>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſonne,</hi> 
                     <note n="r" place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6. Treatis vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on S. Iohn.</note> He hath not that life, which doth not eate that Bread, and drinke that Blood. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, men may haue a temporall life without that, but not at all the eternall. He therefore which doth not eate his fleſh, nor drinke his blood, hath not life in himſelfe, and he which eateth his fleſh, and drinketh his blood, hath life. He anſwereth to both, becauſe he ſayd eternall.</p>
                  <p>It is not ſo in that meate which we receyue for the ſuſtayning of this temporall life; for he which ſhal not receyue it, ſhall not liue<hi>:</hi> yet for all that, he ſhall not liue alwayes, which doth receyue it: for it may come to paſſe, that many which haue taken that meate, may dye by old age, or by a diſeaſe, or by ſome other cauſe. But in this meate and drinke, (that is to ſay, the Body and Blood of our Lord) it is not ſo: for both he which doth not receiue it, hath not life, and he which doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it, hath life, and this likewiſe eternall. Therefore he would haue this bread and drinke, to be vnderſtood the ſociety of the body, and his members, <note n="a" place="margin">Iohn. 14. 20. and 17. 21, 22, 23.</note> which is the holy Church, his Saints and faythfull, &amp;c. The Sacrament of this thing (that is to ſay, of the vnity of the Body &amp; Blood of Chriſt) is prepared on the Lords Table, in ſome place dayly, in ſome place at certayne times, and is receyued from the Lords Table, vnto ſome to life, vnto ſome to deſtruction. But the thing it ſelfe (to which the Sacrament doth belong) is to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man to life, to no man to deſtruction, whoſoeuer ſhall be partaker of it, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here thou art moſt playne indéed, that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked cannot eate and drinke Chriſt Ieſus, the Bread of life. And by this alſo, we finde, that thou dooſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:14"/>
                     <hi>according to S.</hi> Paul <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 3, 4</note> 
                     <hi>that the faithful Iewes did eate and drinke the ſame ſpirituall ſubſtance which we do, (but in their Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, Chriſt to come; in ours, Chriſt is come, the ſame ſpirituall vertue in both;) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe (as thou dooſt affirme) they could not haue entred into eternall life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(True, my ſonne,)</hi> 
                     <note n="c" place="margin">In his Booke of the profit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Chap. 1.</note> Whoſoeuer in Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na vnderſtood Chriſt, did eate the ſame ſpirituall food which we do, &amp;c. To the beleeuer it was neyther this nor that meate and drinke, which belongs to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and thirſty, but to the beleeuer, the ſame which is now: for then, Chriſt to come, now, Chriſt is come: to come, and is come, are diuers words, yet the ſame Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What other difference is there betwéene their Sacramen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s and ours, beſides Chriſt to come, and Chriſt is come?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">In his 26. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eatis vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on S. Iohn.</note> In ſignes they are diuers, but in the thing ſignifyed, they are alike, &amp;c. They did all drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke, but in the viſible appearance, they one thing, we another, but the ſame in ſpirituall vertue, which that ſignifyed, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Hold firmely <hi>(my ſonne)</hi> and make no doubt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <note n="e" place="margin">In his Booke to Peter the Deacon, Chap. 18. 19.</note> the ſame onely begotten Sonne, the word made fleſh, to haue offered himſelfe for vs, a ſweete ſmelling ſauour to God, <note n="f" place="margin">Ephe. 5. 2</note> A ſacrifice and Hoſte, to whom, with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, beaſts were ſacrificed in the time of the old Teſtament, by the Patriarks, Prophets, &amp; Prieſts: and to whom now (that is, in the time of the new Teſtament) with the
<pb facs="tcp:3409:14"/>
Father and the holy Ghoſt, (with whom he is equall in diuinity) the holy Catholike Church through the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall world, ceaſeth not in fayth and loue, to offer the ſacrifice of Bread and wyne; for in thoſe carnall obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, there was a figuration of the fleſh of Chriſt, which for our ſinnes, he without ſinne was to offer, and of the Blood, which he was to ſheade for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of our ſinnes. But in this ſacrifice, there is a thankes-giuing, and alſo a remembrance of the fleſh of Chriſt, which he did offer for vs, and of the blood which the ſame God did ſhead for vs, &amp;c. <note n="g" place="margin">In his 20 Booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Chap. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the comming of Chriſt, the fleſh and blood of this Sacrifice, was promiſed by oblations of ſimilitudes: in the Paſſion of Chriſt, it was deliuered in the trueth it ſelfe: After the Aſcenſion of Chriſt, it is celebrated by a Sacrament of remembrance, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We note here from thée, one thing well worth the nothing, againſt our aduerſaries, that is, if Chriſt be really contayned in the Sacrifice of their Maſſe, then Chriſt, the ſecond perſon in Trinity, is offered to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the ſecond perſon in Trinity. But we aſſure our ſelues, that it cannot ſtand with thy grauity, to allow of ſuch abſurdity. Thou dooſt here call this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, The ſacrifice of Bread &amp; Wine, as it is indéed; for we find in holy Scripture, that the heauen muſt receyue or contayne Chriſt, vntill his ſecond comming:</hi> 
                     <note n="h" place="margin">Acts. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 21.</note> 
                     <hi>and therefore we hold him not to be in diuers places at one time, as in heauen aboue, and in the bread and wine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath: but as thou haſt fully reſolued vs, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate can neyther eate nor drinke Chriſt; and alſo, that the faithfull Iewes did both eate and drinke the ſame ſpirituall foode which we do, euen Chriſt himſelfe,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:15"/>
                     <hi>the ſpirituall Rocke that followed them;</hi> 
                     <note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>ſo we pray thée to reſolue vs alſo, if Chriſt (as he is man) may be in diuers places at once; if not, then how we may hold him here on earth, he being onely in heauen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My ſonne,</hi> 
                     <note n="k" place="margin">In his 30 Treatis vp on S Iohn.</note> Chriſt being abſent, is alſo preſent; vnleſſe he were preſent, we could not hold him; but becauſe it is true which he ſayd, <note n="l" place="margin">Math. 28. 20.</note> Behold, I am with you to the end of the world; both he went away, and is here alſo, he returned, and did not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But how did he both go away, and alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne? Is he preſent here both according to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, as he is God, and alſo according to that ſubſtance which he tooke of the bleſſed Virgin his mother? did not he carry his Body into heauen, and there ſits at the right hand of God?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>He carried his Body into heauen, but he took not his Maieſty away from the world, &amp;c. The poore ye ſhall alwayes haue with you, <hi>(ſayth he)</hi> 
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Iohn 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 8.</note> but me ye ſhall not haue alwayes, &amp;c. He ſpake of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Body: for according to his Maieſty, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his prouidence, according to his infallible and inuiſible grace, it is fulfilled which he ſayd, (Behold, I am with you to the worlds end.) But according to the fleſh which the word did take, according to that which was borne of the Virgin, according to that which was apprehended by the Iewes, which was nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon the Tree, and taken downe from the Croſſe, lapped in linnen clothes, and put in the Sepulchre, which was manifeſted in the reſurrection; Ye ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:3409:15"/>
not haue me alwayes with you. Why? becauſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the preſence of his Body, being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant with his Diſciples fourty dayes, in their ſight he aſcended into heauen, and is not here; for there he ſits at the right hand of his Father; and is here: for the preſence of his Maieſty did not depart. After another ſort, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the preſence of his Maieſty, we haue Chriſt alwayes; according to the preſence of his fleſh, it is truely ſayd to his Diſciples, But me ye ſhall not haue alwayes: for according to the preſence of the fleſh, the Church had him but a few dayes; but now ſhe holds him by fayth, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Notwithſtanding all this playne ſpeach of thine, yet ſome do abſurdly affirme, that thou dooſt here but deny a Viſible preſence onely; and that thou dooſt great (according to Tranſſubſtantion) a corporall preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament, after an inuiſible maner: how ſhall we (from thée) anſwere to that abſurd cauelling?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> His diuinity truely is alwayes with vs, <note n="n" place="margin">In his 60 Sermon vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on S. Iohn.</note> but vnleſſe he were abſent corporally, we ſhould alwayes carnally ſee his body, &amp;c. <note n="o" place="margin">In his 2. Sermon vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the birth of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ord.</note> The Word being made fleſh, it is euident, God and man, two, to be in one fleſh; ſometime man ſpeaketh to the Father, ſometime God; ſometime viſible from his mother, ſometime inuiſible from his Father, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But God is omnipotent, and therefore by his omnipotent power, he may, (as ſome thinke) be both in heauen, and alſo corporally inuiſible in the Sacrament, and occupy no place; for he may (ſay they) take away ſpaces of places from Bodyes, and yet the Bodyes may</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:16"/>
                     <hi>remayne ſtill: and ſo he himſelfe both God and man, to be both here and there at one time.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne,)</hi> God is in ſuch wiſe omnipotent, <note n="p" place="margin">In his 284. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</note> that he neuer pulls in ſunder the inſtitutions of his owne order, &amp;c. <note n="q" place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. Booke againſt Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus. Chap. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> According to a corporall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, Chriſt could not be at one time, both in the Sunne and Moone, and vpon the Croſſe, &amp;c. <note n="r" place="margin">In his 57. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>danus.</note> We muſt take heede, that we do not ſo build vp the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the man, that we take away the trueth of the Body, &amp;c. Take away the ſpaces of places from Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, and they are no where, and becauſe they be no where, they are not at all. Take away Bodyes from the qualities of Bodyes, and there ſhall not be any place where they may be: and therefore of neceſſity it muſt be, that they haue no being, &amp;c. If the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a body (how little or great ſoeuer it be) be vtterly taken away, there ſhalbe no place where his qualityes may be, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thou haſt now fully reſolued vs in this laſt poynt, touching Chriſt to be onely in heauen; and it doth euidently appeare alſo by theſe few wordes from thée, that the formes and accidents of Bread and wine, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not remayne without their ſubſtances (as ſome do vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagine) but that it is truely Bread which we ſée in the bleſſed Sacrament, euen as our eyes do declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(Verily, my ſonne)</hi> 
                     <note n="ſ" place="margin">In his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to the children, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Bede vpon the 1. and 10. to the Cor.</note> That which ye ſee, is Bread and the cup, which alſo the eyes do declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: But as touching that which your fayth requireth to be inſtructed in, the bread is the Body of Chriſt, and
<pb facs="tcp:3409:16"/>
the Cup is the blood.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But Chriſt being now in heauen onely, (as thou dooſt affirme) how is that Bread his Body, or the cup, or that which is in the cup, how is it his blood?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe things <hi>(my ſonne)</hi> are therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sacraments, becauſe in them, one thing is ſeene, another thing is vnderſtood; That which is ſeene, hath a corporall forme; That which is vnderſtood, hath a ſpirituall profit: Therefore if thou wilt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Body of Chriſt, heare the Apoſtle, ſaying, <note n="t" place="margin">1. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 27.</note> Ye are the body of Chriſt, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We do ſo, diuine</hi> Auguſtine: <hi>for this matter, we both heare him and note him, not in that place onely, but in diuers other places alſo;</hi> 
                     <note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 5. 1. Cor. 6, 15. &amp; 10. 16, 17. Ephe. 1. 22, 23, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 4. &amp;c. to 17. &amp; 5. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. &amp;c. to the end.</note> 
                     <hi>and therefore the faithfull cannot miſtake thée herein, thou agréeing ſo well with holy Scripture. But wherefore dooſt thou write in ſome place, that Chriſt did carry himſelfe in his owne hands, when he did deliuer to his diſciples, the Sacrament of his Body and Blood? And againe, though</hi> Iudas <hi>receyued it vnworthily, yet thou ſayeſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that the ſame Sacrament was to him likewiſe, the Body and Blood of Chriſt. Thou ſéemeſt thereby to contradict thy former ſpeaches here vttered touching the ſame thing: declare vnto vs therefore the cauſe, why thou diddeſt write after that maner.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> If Sacraments <note n="x" place="margin">In his 23. Epiſtle to Boniface.</note> had not ſome ſimilitude o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> likeneſſe of theſe things whereof they be Sacraments, they ſhould not be Sacraments at all; and from this ſimilitude, moſt commonly they receyue the
<pb facs="tcp:3409:17"/>
names alſo of the ſame things: ſo that after a certayne maner, the Sacrament of the Body of Chriſt, is the Body of Chriſt: The Sacrament of the Blood of Chriſt is the Blood of Chriſt, &amp;c. <hi>(And therefore, as I ſayd before,</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 18. at the letter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o.</note>) Our Lord doubted not to ſay, This is my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, when he gaue the ſigne <hi>(or Sacrament)</hi> of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Undoubtedly, thou haſt layd open this matter alſo very playne; for indéed, after a certayne maner, both Chriſt carryed himſelfe in his owne hands, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo</hi> Iudas <hi>did eate and drinke the Body and Blood of our Lord. But dooſt thou allow it lawfull for any man to follow the literall ſence in a contrary reſpect, that is, with a carnall ſeruitude to take the ſignes for the things ſignified by them, and ſo to reuerence the Sacrament, as the thing it ſelfe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> The Lord himſelfe, <note n="y" place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Booke of Chriſtian doctrine. Chap. 9.</note> and the Apoſtolical diſcipline, hath deliuered ſome few ſignes for many, and the ſame moſt eaſie to be done, and moſt reuerend to be vnderſtood, and moſt pure in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation; as is the Sacrament of Baptiſme, and the Celebration of the Body &amp; Blood of our Lord; which things, euery one (being inſtructed when he recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth) acknowledgeth to what they are referred, that he reuerence them not with a carnall ſeruitude, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a ſpirituall liberty, &amp;c. But as to follow the letter, and to take the ſignes for the things which are ſignified by them, comes of ſeruile infirmity; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to interpret the ſignes vnprofitable, proceedes from the euill of wandring errour, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3409:17"/>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe laſt words of thine (moſt reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) are inuincible againſt the doctrine herein of our Romiſh aduerſaryes: for if hereafter they ſhall boaſt, that thou dooſt agrée with their Tranſſubſtantiation, &amp; carnall aderation in the Maſſe; we will then demaund of them, what other thing it is to follow the letter, &amp; to take the ſignes for the things ſignified, (and ſo to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence them with a carnall ſeruitude) but the ſelfe-ſame carnall doctrine of Tranſſubſtantiation? And therefore we will now reſt fully ſatiſfied with theſe thy former ſpeaches, as being from thee a ſufficient witneſſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in againſt them. And the better to approue this thy doctrine to be the doctrine of the Church, aboue a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeeres ſince, we will ioyne here with thee, a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or two more from Antiquity, that by the mouth of two or three witneſſes,</hi> 
                     <note n="z" place="margin">2. Cor. 13. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>the Trueth may be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Speake, diuine</hi> Hierome, <hi>what is thy true opinion, touching this matter now in controuerſie, about the myſtery or Sacrament of the Body and Blood of our Lord. Speake briefly (learned Father:) yet let it be ſo effectuall, that thy words may playnely declare thy meaning.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hierome.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne,)</hi> 
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Vpon the 147. Pſalm.</note> I thinke the Goſpell the Body of Ieſus, &amp;c. And where he ſayth, He which ſhall not eate my fleſh, and drinke my blood, &amp;c. <note n="b" place="margin">Iohn. 6. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> although it may be vnderſtood in the myſtery, yet more truely the word of the Scripture is the Body and Blood of Chriſt. The doctrine is diuine. <note n="c" place="margin">Looke the 26. Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mily of S. Aug. and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. Chap. 22. and note how he doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with this of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Hierom</note> If at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time we go to the myſtery, he which is faithfull, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth it; If he fall into a ſpot, he is in danger;
<pb facs="tcp:3409:18"/>
If at any time we heare the word of GOD, both the word of God, and the fleſh of Chriſt, and his blood, is powred into our eares, and we think an other thing, to what great danger we runne into, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verily thou haſt here (according to our deſire) briefly ſpoken to the purpoſe indéed, and it may well ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for a teſtimony from thée, againſt that ſtrange doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of Tranſſubſtantiation; for according thereunto, we know not how the holy Scripture can be ſo truely the Body and Blood of Chriſt, as the holy myſtery: and therefore, becauſe yea or nay is a ſufficient anſwere, we will content our ſelues, onely with this thy briefe affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation herein, and ſo procéede to the third witneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Speake, diuine</hi> Theodoret, <hi>what ſayeſt thou, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of our Lord?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theodoret.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> 
                     <note n="d" place="margin">All this from Theo. is to be found in his 1. and 2. Dialogue.</note> Thou knoweſt that God called his Body, Bread. <note n="e" place="margin">Iohn. 6. 51.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I know it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theodoret.</speaker>
                  <p>Moreouer, in another place, he named wheate, fleſh. <note n="f" place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I know this to be true alſo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
                  <p>In the tradition of myſteries, he called bread his Body, and that which powred and commixed in the cup, Blood.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So he did call theſe things indéed; but did he rightly call them ſo, as being his naturall Body and</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:18"/>
                     <hi>Blood? or did he but change the names?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> That which is a body according to nature, ſhall rightly be called a body, and likewiſe blood, &amp;c. But our Sauiour changed the names veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and impoſed to the body, that name which rightly belonged to the ſigne and Symbole, but to the ſigne he impoſed that name which belonged to the body; ſo when he had named himſelfe a Vyne, he called that Blood, which was the ſigne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the nature of the Bread and wine ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning, what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of the alteration of the names?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
                  <p>To thoſe that are admitted to <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     </hi> diuine myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes, the inſtitution is manifeſt; for he would not haue them which are partakers of the diuine myſteries, to regard the nature of thoſe things which are ſeene, but by the changing of the names, to beleeue the alteration which is made by grace; for he which named that, Wheat and Bread, which by nature is a body, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, named himſelfe a Vine, he hath honored the Symboles and ſignes which are ſeene, with the name of the Body and Blood, not verily changing nature, but adding grace to nature, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What ſayſt thou then to thoſe Heretiks, which hold, that as thoſe ſignes of the Body and Blood of our Lord, were one kind of things before the inuecation of the Prieſt (or miniſter) and after are changed and made other things, euen ſo the Body of our Lord alſo, after the reſurrection, is changed into the diuine ſubſtance?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theo.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> 
                     <note n="g" place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>. Dialoges</note> They are taken in their
<pb facs="tcp:3409:19"/>
owne ſnares; for neyther do the miſticall ſignes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from their owne nature after ſanctificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but they remayne in the former ſubſtance, and figure, and forme, &amp;c. Compare the ſigne with the trueth, &amp; thou ſhalt vnderſtand the ſimilitude; for the figure ought to be like the trueth: for truely, that body hath the firſt forme, and figure, and circumſcription, and (that I may ſay at once) the ſubſtance of a body, but it was made immortall after the reſurrection, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moſt true it is (graue Father) Chriſt hath ſtill the true ſubſtance of a Body, and therefore (the ſigne and the thing ſignified being alike) thoſe Heretickes, whoſoeuer they be, that ſéeme to proue the forme of Bread in the Sacrament, to be there without the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Bread, do thereby ſéeme to proue alſo, Chriſt to a haue a fantaſticall Body, that is, a Body in ſhew, without the ſubſtance of a body. But thou dooſt here moſt playnely confute that palpable abſurdity, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou art agréeable to the true doctrine of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church; for what Chriſtian liuing a thouſand yeres ſince, or vpwards, did euer affirme ſuch a reall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in the Sacrament, that thereby Chriſt God and man, is to be ſwallowed into the bodyes of many dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned creatures? We find many proofes from Antiquity to the contrary, as partly hath bene noted already; and yet for more witneſſe thereof, we note S.</hi> Ambroſe <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, who ſayth playnely, touching this ſacred Bread, (euen Chriſt himſelfe) that</hi> it is not bread which goeth into the body, <note n="h" place="margin">In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Booke of Sacraments, Chap. 4.</note> but the Bread of eternall life, which ſtrengthneth the ſubſtance of our ſoules, &amp;c. <hi>He ſayth not (as ſome peruerſly miſconſter him) Non tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e in corpus per nutritionem:</hi> 
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Bellarm. vpon the Euchariſt, the 2. Booke &amp; 14. Chap.</note> it paſſeth not through
<pb facs="tcp:3409:19"/>
the body, by nouriſhment; but, <hi>Non vadit in corpus:</hi> it goeth not into the body, &amp;c. <hi>Who then can miſtake him here, but he that wilfully makes himſelfe ignorant, euen he which by ſuch vndirect dealing, peruerts thy words alſo, ſaying,</hi> 
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Bellarm. in the ſame Booke, Chap. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>Where thou dooſt affirme the Bread and wine to remayne after ſanctification (both in ſubſtance, nature, figure and forme as they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,) thou dooſt thereby meane, onely the ſenſible acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and viſible formes do ſo remayne, but the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to be changed? But if ſuch weake defending of errours be allowed for good and lawfull, in vayne then it is to bring any teſtimony from antiquity againſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes. But we hope, that ſuch peruerſe anſweres from the peruerter, may proue in good time, a good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue for the peruerted, to looke about him betimes, and not both to liue and dye a childe in vnderſtanding; for ignorance cannot excuſe thoſe that wilfully refuſe to walke by the light of holy Scripture.</hi> The word of God is a lanterne vnto my feete, and a light vnto my paths, <hi>(ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet</hi> Dauid<note n="*" place="margin">Pſalm. 119.</note>) It is as a light ſhining in a dark place <hi>(ſayth S.</hi> Peter. <note n="*" place="margin">2. Pet. 1.</note>) <hi>By which we are giuen to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that as the Sunne giues light to the corporall eye, ſo doth the holy Scripture giue light to the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eye. Whereupon it followes, that if neyther our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaryes nor our ſelues would wilfully become blind, (and then truſt to the leading of others) we ſhould ſoone all agrée in one outward profeſſion: for who is he that can beleeue, contrary to that which he ſéeeth? or where is that ſpirituall man, ſo contentious, as not to allow thoſe Traditions and cuſtomes of the Church, which are not contrary to the expreſſe word of God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We grant from the Sacrament, (according to that trueth which we finde in holy Scripture</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 6. 63.</note>) <hi>the true ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:20"/>
                     <hi>&amp; drinking of the fleſh and blood of Chriſt, ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; (we ſay word for word, as Saint</hi> Baſil <hi>ſaid aboue a thouſand yeeres ſince;</hi> 
                     <note n="l" place="margin">In his 141. Epiſtle.</note> We eate his fleſh, and drinke his blood, being made partakers of him by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation and ſenſible life of the word and wiſdome: for he called all his myſticall conuerſation in the fleſh, fleſh and blood, and made manifeſt that doctrine which depends of his life, actuall, naturall, and diuine, by which the ſoule is nouriſhed, exerciſed, and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp to the contemplation of heauenly things, &amp;c.) <hi>but we deny ſuch a groſſe eating and drinking therein, that thereby both the righteous and the vnrighteous are made partakers of Chriſt; which doctrine is moſt manifeſt againſt the ſacred Scripture:</hi> 
                     <note n="m" place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>we deny alſo ſuch a groſſe eating &amp; drinking therein, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Lay people muſt not communicate with the bleſſed cup of our Lord, fearing leſt they ſhould ſhead his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctous blood vpon their garments: or leſt by the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſtomackes, they ſhould bring vp againe their Creator by belchings and vomitings; which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity, the Church hath long ſince confuted, as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth S.</hi> Aug. <note n="n" place="margin">Againſt Fauſtus the 20 Booke, and Chap. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>for indéed, according to the doctrine of her head Chriſt Ieſus, ſo doth the true Church teach alwayes; But neuer did the true Church teach, that our Sauiour Chriſt hath any reall being in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of a wicked creature; for Chriſt himſelfe is moſt playne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that vayne doctrine. And briefly to proue that to be true, we will now ſet aſide all other witneſſes and proofes whatſoeuer, and humbly beſéech the author of this bleſſed Sacrament (euen Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe) to reſolue vs herein.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Speake, holy Lambe of God, thou that art the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sauiour of the world, &amp; ſpeake ſo, we moſt humbly</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:20"/>
                     <hi>beſéech thée, that thy words herein may proue a ſwéete ſauour of life, to the ſmall remnant of thy holy Church in this corrupt age. Teach vs (ſwéete Lord) whether any can haue true life, without eating and drinking that bleſſed fleſh and blood of thine; and alſo, whether any can miſſe of that true life, eating and drinking the ſame bleſſed foode.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> 
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Iohn. 6. 48. to 36.</note> I am that Bread of life: your fathers did eate Manna in the wilderneſſe, and are dead: This is that bread which came downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that he which eateth of it, ſhould not dye. I am that liuing bread which came downe from heauen: If any man eate of this bread, he ſhall liue for euer: and the bread that I will giue, is my fleſh, which I will giue for the life of the world, &amp;c. Verily verily I ſay vnto you, except ye eate the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinke his blood, ye haue no life in you. Whoſoeuer eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, hath eternall life, and I will rayſe him vp at the laſt day: for my fleſh is meate indeed, and my blood is drinke indeed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lord and God, theſe words of thine are profound, and to the ſpirituall man, ſpirit and life, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though to the carnall man, farre otherwiſe; for notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding thou haſt commaunded vs all, not to adde any thing to thy ſacred word,</hi> 
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 2, and 12. 32. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 22. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>yet theſe carnall-minded men can not vnderſtand theſe thy comfortable ſpeeches, vnleſſe they adde thereunto ſome matter of their owne deuiſing, as namely, by adding a condition to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly text, more then thou didſt there expreſſe<note n="*" place="margin">Bellarmine in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>: as though there were a defect in thy word, by which all things are made perfit, and by which, at the laſt day, they ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> iudge both the quicke and the dead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:21"/>
                     <hi>But full well do thy faithfull people, know by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of thy holy ſpirit, that thou giueſt not thy ſelfe for foode to any reprobate and vnworthy creature; for thou ſayſt here moſt playnely; that whoſoeuer eateth and drinketh thy fleſh and blood, hath eternall life: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, although the Sacrament thereof may be eaten and drunken, both by the worthy and vnworthy receiuer, (as witneſſeth thine Apoſtle</hi> Paul) <note n="q" place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 27.</note> 
                     <hi>yet that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed foode it ſelfe cannot ſo be eaten and drunken: for the vertue thereof is, to giue life to all that eates and drinks it; and this is thy promiſe which can neuer be broken.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But, moſt gracious Lord, foraſmuch as there be yet many weake people, that cannot well vnderſtand thée herein, without adding to theſe thy words, this word (worthyly) reſolue them we (humbly beſéech thée) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſo or not, that ſome profeſſed Chriſtians may eate and drinke this ſacred banket of thine (euen thy ſelfe) vnworthily, and ſo dye in their ſinnes, as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy and faithleſſe Iewes did, notwithſtanding they did eate Manna. Speake ſo vnto them, (good Lord) that they may both heare and vnderſtand.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(My ſonne)</hi> Let thoſe weake people of little faith, marke well here, what I ſay vnto them:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Haue not I graciouſly giuen you warning by my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred word, ſaying,)</hi> 
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Math. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. and 15. 9.</note> Take heede, and beware of the leauen of the Phariſes and Sadduces? in vaine they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines, mens precepts. <hi>(Haue not I taught you by mine Apoſtle</hi> Paul) faith is by hearing, and hearing by the word of God? <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 10. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Iohn. 8. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Mark. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 24.</note>He that is of God, heareth Gods wordes, &amp;c. <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 5. 39.</note> Are ye not therfore deceiued, becauſe ye know not the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, neyther the power of God? *Search the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb facs="tcp:3409:21"/>
My ſheepe heare my voyce, and I know them, <note place="margin">Iohn 10. 27. and 12. 48. and 14. 6. Luke. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1. 23.</note> and they follow me. He that refuſeth me, and recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not my words, hath one that iudgeth him: the word that I haue ſpoken, it ſhall iudge him in the laſt day. I am the Way, the Trueth, &amp; the Life. No man commeth vnto the Father, but by me. <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>He that is not with me, is againſt me: and he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth. <hi>(but)</hi> * He that eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him. As that liuing Father hath ſent me, ſo liue I by the Father, and he that eateth me, euen he ſhall liue by me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>(Note well here what I ſay, I ſpeake not one thing and meane an other; I make not my promiſe ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, and meane it but conditionally; I ſay not, he that eateth me worthily, becauſe no vnworthy creature that ſhall dye in his ſinne, can eate me; And to make that moſt playne vnto you, I ſay againe as I haue ſayd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready)</hi> This is that bread which came downe from heauen, not as your fathers haue eaten Manna, and are dead, he that eateth of this bread, ſhall liue for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lay.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For this thy playne declaration, all prayſe be giuen vnto thée, O Lord: for hereby, all may diſcerne moſt clearely, that thou dooſt not commit thy ſelfe to vnfaithfull creatures, and to be foode for the reprobate, as</hi> Iudas, <hi>and ſuch like: We therefore moſt humbly pray thée to open the eyes of theſe blinde weakelings, which (by too much eſtabliſhing the doctrines of men) go about to contradict thée herein, and ſo inſpire their heartes with the grace of thy holy ſpirit, that they may thereby diſcerne the onely cauſe of their great blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; (But the ſame cauſe being by thy gracious help</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:22"/>
                     <hi>taken away, they ſhall then clearely ſée to ſéeke and find, euen according to thy diuine direction.</hi> 
                     <note n="ſ" place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Let them ſée (O Lord) that their Church of Rome doth yet erre, and will erre ſtill, vntill ſhée acknowledge her owne weakeneſſe that ſhe may erre.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But ſo aboundant is thy goodneſſe &amp; mercy towards repentant ſinners, that if ſhe would in due time repent her former errours, with that vayne and preſumptuous opinion touching her ſuppoſed purity, in her owne doctrine generally; no doubt, thou wouldſt not onely pardon all her erronious doctrines, and ſuperſtitious cerimonies; but alſo reſtore her to her firſt dignity and commendation, and cauſe all her good and laudable Traditions and Cuſtomes, (which now, in reſpect of her wilfull blindneſſe in ſome poynts, are little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing regarded by a great number) to be as highly eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and as duely obſerued, as euer heretofore they haue bene: for thy eternall wiſedome doth more reſpect the good and faithfull intent of the dooer, then the déed done, whatſoeuer it be; becauſe whatſoeuer is not of true faith, (ſéeme it neuer ſo holy in the ſight of man) is no better then ſinne, in thy infallible Iudgement<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14. 23.</note>.</hi> 
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In conſideration whereof, we moſt humbly beſéech thée alſo to encreaſe in vs (Proteſtants) true and liuely faith, which alwayes worketh by loue, that we may be all in generall more zealous in thy ſeruice, then hither to we haue bene; for we here acknowledge before thée that knoweſt the ſecrets of all hearts, who alſo hereafter ſhalt be our Iudge, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge without true zeale, is more vnprofitable in thy ſight, then zeale without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:</hi> 
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Math. 21. 28. to 32. Luke. 12. 47, 48. Iohn 9. 41. Actes. 10. 1. 10 5. Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 5. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>therefore as we profeſſe thée in words, ſo (good Lord) let vs expreſſe thée in workes, that we may not be reckoned in the number of thoſe fooliſh men, that</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:22"/>
                     <hi>build vpon ſand, that is, thoſe that heare thy words, and do them not.</hi> 
                     <note n="u" place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 26. 27.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We profeſſe before thy diuine Maieſty, that none can be ſaued, but thoſe that haue a faith working by loue,</hi> 
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Gala. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 6. 1. Tim. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Tit. 3. 8. Iames. 2. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>other faiths we hold as dead, and vayne, in reſpect of Iuſtification, but that faith onely which worketh by loue, we hold to iuſtifie without the workes of the law, euen as thine holy Apoſtle hath taught vs.</hi> 
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore, for the great loue in thée declared vnto vs, when thou didſt ſuffer torments &amp; death for our ſinnes, we beſéech thée (ſwéete Ieſus) ſo to bleſſe the hearts of all true Chriſtians, that they may all from hencefoorth both liue and dye in peace and vnity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Behold, (ſayth thy Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Pſalm. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>) how good &amp; how comely a thing it is, brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dwell euen together. It is like the precious oyntment vpon the head, that runneth downe vpon the beard, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto <hi>Aarons</hi> beard, which went downe on the border of his garments<hi>:</hi> and as the dew of Hermon, which falleth vpon the Mountaynes of Zion<hi>:</hi> for there the Lord appoynted the bleſſing and life for euer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let thine heauenly bleſſing therefore ſo bleſſe the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall Church here on earth, that it may euen now (without any more controuerſies) conclude a ſpirituall marriage as it were betwéene faith and workes, that ſo wée may all both truely glorifie thée in this world, &amp; alſo be made partakers with thée of that euerlaſting felicity in the next world, euen in that holy place of en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>leſſe ioy, which from the foundations of the world hath bene pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for thine elect,</hi> 
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. 24,</note> 
                     <hi>by thine heauenly Father, our</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3409:23"/>
                     <hi>onely God and Creator, to whom with thée our ſwéete Redéemer, and the holy Ghoſt our ſanctifier, (thrée perſons, and one euerliuing God) be aſcribed all prayſe, power, honor, dominion and glory, both now and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Let no man deceiue himſelfe: If any man among you ſeeme to be wiſe in this world, let him be a foole, that he may be wiſe: for the wiſdome of this world is fooliſhneſſe with God, &amp;c.</p> 
                  <bibl>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 18, 19.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <closer>
               <hi>Laus Deo, et pax Chriſtianis.</hi> Glory be to God, and peace among Chriſtians.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faults eſcaped.</head>
            <p>In Page 5. line 23. for a principall, Read the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall. Page 12. line 24. for, (ſayth he) knoweth God, Read, ſayth, he knoweth God, Page 24. line 5. in the mergent, for Page 18. Read, Page 15.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3409:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
